Now I'm going to talk to you about how to decide if you are going to build a glue in or a bolt in neck.
And I want to explain the differences to you of each of these types of designs and how they affect the sound and how they'll affect your ability to build one.
Let's begin with what's called a bolt on neck.
As you can see once again, we talked about that it has four screws that hold it in.
And of course they don't protrude through the top.
The benefits of the bolt on neck are that you can easily adjust the angle of the neck by applying shims under it.
A small piece of wood, a small piece of paper, whatever to tilt the neck if you need to change the angle of the neck.
Also if you ever break the neck or, lets go ahead and assume that at some point during the assembly process you have difficulty, shall we say, with the neck that you're working on and you decide that you want to start over.
You will be able to do that with absolutely no problem, it won't affect your body at all.
You can complete the body first, make sure that it's done, make sure it's going to work, and then turn your attention to a neck.
Now bolt on necks are not as warm in sound as glue in necks, but they are definitely going to be something that you would be able to pull off.
This is what's referred to as a glue in neck again.
And again this neck is actually glued in to the body, it is not removeable once it's put in there.
For these guitars, the only way to take the neck out and put a new one in is to cut this neck out and route all of the material that's left from it, from this body.
So again this is something that is very difficult to change.
If you break the neck, it woud be very difficult for you to make another one to replace.
In addition the fit between this neck and the body has to be fairly precise for you to get the appropriate return of vibration and tone.
It requires a little more technical skill, you have to be a lot more careful when you're putting this type of guitar together.
But again it provides a very solid joint, it is a permanent neck, so if you don't like this neck you can't really change it.
But again it's a solid connection.
You'll get more sustain with this type of neck then you will with a bolt on.